[Music]
well you're in luck this is the last
lecture that you'll see of
me that's quite a relief isn't it
and the
during the first hour I'd like to
summarize everything that we did that's
why I gave the table contents and
effectively what I shall do is to again
write down the table
contents on the black
balls but they're all printed for you so
you don't have to copy anything take any
notes but remind ourselves what we did
in each section in what order what came
out what was important and how every
everything was used and fit together and
then that's not going to take too long I
hope and after the break I'll show you
something
interesting the course we had was called
topology and geometry but it could have
also been called pictorial
thinking and
in
2014 we started in the first chapter um
who was missing the table contents there
were two people um there and there thank
you very much yeah we began with the
catalog of most important manifolds
you remember so this was
the section on
examples that were needed in order to
build further examples all the manifolds
all the geometric figures in the world
can be built up by combining these in
various ways we had the
B the
sphere or which is the boundary of that
B that Dimension One F
the cube of Dimension M you can dissect
such cubes for example by cutting and so
on and we also
had Tor Tas plural which is toride t² is
the standard two dimensional surface of
a
donut also my initials
T and also we had the famous M strip
it can be twisted any number of times
and cut it along the center you get a
different results also something called
a
climber you might remember and the
simplest way I find of drawing this is
something like that it's a it's a bottle
which joins up itself but in a funny
sort of way there's
also the real projective plane and by
combining
in
cor you had the re surface of genus G
that was orientable
and the non surfaces of Gus G combining
out the2 the projected plant so we had
all those things and also we had
operations of
manifolds what do we mean well given
those ingredients basic manifolds you
could
do some sort of calculation with them or
you could add multiply and so on or take
um
quotients all that you could take the
boundary for example of the ball and get
this
sphere the cube is homeomorphic table so
if you take the boundary you also get
the sphere although it has corners but
that's okay topologically they're
indistinguishable all the others all the
others not um taus clim rp2 these do not
have boundary movie strip does have a
does have a boundary if you have the
standard movie strip which twists once
what is its
boundary it's not two circles a single
Circle which is quite interesting okay
so you could take the boundary you could
also um do the product familiar
operation from elementary mathematics
cartisian or direct product as you know
and also you can can quotient
also known as identification space you
introduce an equivalence relation and
that's the quo and finally a funny
operation called surgery or connected
sound as you remember and you can do all
sorts of things with
mols so having prepared the ground
having prepared a catalog of all the
examples that we can
have we then discussed the idea of
isotopy carefully that's what we
sometimes informally call deformation
deforming something you isotope
something and the key concept this is
not a standard piece of terminology in
the mathematical world so I put it
between quotation marks was overflow
depending on how big your ambient space
was how many dimensions you had around
you Freedom two sub manifolds
may or may not
intersect and if you have an M
dimensional manifold and K dimensional
and L dimensional sub manifolds whether
they intersected or not generically
depended on k + L minus M you see K plus
L is what you have to put in and M is
how much room there is so that
difference tells you how much overflow
there is if k + l - M is negative
that's okay um there's a lot of room so
they don't intersect if they did you can
just shake the picture and detach them
that's the case in for example three
dimensional space m is3 one dimensional
curve one dimensional curve where they
might very unlikely intersect but
usually they don't okay one dimensional
curve and one dimensional curve do not
meet in three dimensional space the
Overflow is 1 + 1 - 3 that's negative
but if the Overflow is zero think of the
case two dimensional surface and one
dimensional
curve piercing along the surface in
threedimensional Space 1 + 2 - 3 is zero
that means that they meet in a Zero
Dimensional Subspace Zero Dimensional
that's point and you cannot get rid of
this intersection by
peration if you move you get this zero
intersection somewhere okay and if the
Overflow is positive think of the case
when you have two surfaces of Dimension
two Dimension two and dimension two in
dimension three well 2 + 2 - 3 that's
one there is an overflow one dimension
which means that the the intersection
must be along a onedimensional
Subspace okay and Etc and when we
discuss the moving or isotop things
overflow became important but you needed
one more d Dimension extra dimension in
order to isotope things so overflow
controls and the dimension of
intersection that's what we
learned and then we had of course the
idea of isotopy itself and our notation
that's fair s notation was this
tdle
okay how do we use these Concepts the
all the catalog of basic manifolds and
what you can do with them together with
the idea of
deformation our entire theory was based
on the concept of intersection
number this is the central concept of
this
course if I may digress
slightly modern topology has developed
in terms of something called homology
and homotopy those are are the two great
currents of topology and really useful
ways of looking at the world homology
and homotopy they are related there is
also dual Concepts called cohomology and
koty but intersection number is really
the easiest thing to calculate and it is
in some sense the baby model of homology
theory and a little bit of homotopy so
that is why when I designed the course
at as I decided to base everything at
intersection number because it does not
need much preparation as you saw we
found it fairly easy to think of what an
intersection number was a picture of
intersection number its properties but
as you also saw it's powerful enough for
most
applications so that's why we talked
about intersection number that's why we
based the entire course on the concept
intersection number the main idea was
that you
counted the number of
Crossings but not all intersections are
counted + one some were counted plus one
some were counted minus one depending on
the orientation match or mismatch so
counting intersection
points with
signs + one - one
plusus and
this unit between
submanifolds whose overflow is exactly
zero so that those two subs meet or
intersect in
points
okay you remember this I hope and
then the key concept
really the central concept of this of
course intersection number itself which
we denoted by this strength symbol
little circle so K little circle l in
that order if you instead of consider L
small Circle K K you have to look after
the sign change okay and the really
important
theorem that was I believe theorem 17
it's so important that I even remember
the number you don't have
to theorem which is the theoretical
foundation for the entire course and
which is also easy to visualize is that
this intersection number is invariant
and isot in other words when you deform
the picture this intersection number
does not change it is a physicist would
say a conserved quantity like energy and
other things but it is
true that it this intersection number is
isotopy invariant only for closed subes
closed means compact without boundary
you
recall that if you have boundaries well
the intersection points can fall off the
boundary or appear from the boundary so
you don't get this uh
invariance so that means
without whether the boundary of a sub
manifold is empty or not therefore is
very important okay and also we
discussed let me write ADV as a an
immediate application the generalization
of what is called Jordan curve theorem
which taboka has seen um the in the two
dimensional version it says that if you
have a closed loop which does not
intersect itself however complicated it
is that Loop separates this entire plane
into two components interior and
exterior but we saw this using
intersection theory for the generalized
version if you are in an M dimensional
space and you draw an M minus one
dimensional hypers surface which does
not intersect the it doesn't cross
itself such a hypersurface separates the
space into interior and exterior two
components so generalization of Jordan C
theorem this theorem is supposed to be
extremely difficult to prove but we saw
at least in our framework how easy to do
so and that's entirely thanks to the way
the theory set up in a very pictorial
fashion